<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!-- $Id: pearfaq.xml,v 1.26 2001-11-19 15:54:34 alexmerz Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V1.7//EN"
          "../../phpdoc/dbxml/docbookx.dtd">

<article class="faq">
 <artheader>
  <title>PEAR-Developer FAQ</title>
  <date>$Date: 2001-11-19 15:54:34 $</date>
  <version>$Revision: 1.26 $</version>
 </artheader>

 <qandaset>
  <qandaentry>
   <question title="What is PEAR exactly?" />
    <answer>
     <author name="Tomas V.V. Cox"/>
      <para>
        The PEAR concept it self is only a Repository, a unique web repository
        and the works done in this area (pear web and pear installer/packager)
        are in this direction. Also it's not a common repository, is a
        repository with software that:
        <simplelist>
         <member>
          has been approved to be in by the Pear developers and has the general
          concensus of the Pear community (Pear users)
         </member>
         <member>
          follows a unique coding standard (avaible to read, already standarized
          and used in all PEAR)
         </member>
         <member>
          uses a common error handling mechanism
         </member>
         <member>
          tries to have a similar way of use
         </member>
         <member>
          has documentation about its API in the PHPDoc format
         </member>
         <member>
          has documentation/examples/tests (to be marked as stable)
         </member>
        </simplelist>
      </para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
 
  <qandaentry>
   <question title="How to become a PEAR contributer and/or how to get CVS access to PEAR?" />
    <answer>
     <author name="Alexander Merz"/>
      <para>
       The rules are the same like the ones for getting a PHP CVS account.
       This means you should do one of the following things to improve your
       chances to get a CVS account.
       <simplelist>
	 <member>
         Send <faqlink faq="2">patches</faqlink> for existing PEAR classes.
        </member>
	 <member>
         Create and <emphasis>maintain</emphasis> a new class for PEAR.
        </member>
	 <member>
         Rewrite and <emphasis>maintain</emphasis> an existing class to
         match the <ulink
         url="http://php.net/manual/pear.standards.php">PEAR Coding
         Standards</ulink>.
        </member>
	</simplelist>
       Requesting an account without having existing source code or
       public pre-work does not make much sense.
      </para>
      <para>
       See also <ulink url="http://www.php.net/cvs-php.php">Using
       CVS for PHP Development</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
       You should announce your intention of commiting new stuff to
       the PEAR developers list. It's strongly recommended to
       subscribe to the list. See the <ulink
       url="http://pear.php.net/support.php">support page</ulink>
       for information about subscribing.
      </para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="How to contribute patches?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Alexander Merz, Tomas V.V. Cox"/>
    <para>
     The best possibility to contribute patches is to send them to the
     PEAR developers list <ulink url="mailto:pear-dev@lists.php.net"
     name="pear-dev@lists.php.net"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Make sure your patch is based on a current CVS snapshot. Don't send
     the complete file(s). Use diff or the diff command of CVS and
     attach the output of diff to the mail.
    </para>
    <para>
     Another possibility is to send the patches directly to the
     author(s) of the class. But sometimes the author isn't the
     maintainer, in vacation or has no access to CVS at the
     moment. So better use the mailinglist.
    </para>
    <para>
     Recommend way for generating patches:
     <simplelist>
      <member>
       <command># cd /cvs/php.net/pear/NET_Ping</command>
      </member>
      <member>
       Retrieve the latest version
       <command># cvs update</command>
      </member>
      <member>
       Make the modifications you want
       <command># editor Ping.php</command>
      </member>
      <member>
       Check if there have been no modifications while you was modifing
       the file. If there were, re-adapt your patch to this
       last release.
       <command># cvs update</command>
      </member>
      <member>
       Generate the patch against the latest version from CVS
       <command># cvs diff -u Ping.php > ping_diff.txt</command>
      </member>
     </simplelist>
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="How to contribute patches for Outlook Express users" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Alexander Merz"/>
    <para>
     The mailing list software accepts only attachments of the
     content type "text/plain". OE creates the content type of a
     attachment by checking the file ending. So make sure that the
     diff output, if stored in a file, the file has an ending,
     which is assigned to a program like Notepad
     (plain-text editors). So better rename your diff file to "file-diff.txt"
     before attach it.
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="I want to contribute, in what areas could I do it?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Alexander Merz"/>
    <para>
     The general directory for new PEAR-classes and modules is
     pear/ in the CVS repository. The name of the directory of the
     new class is build from the class name and the package name.
     If you wrote a class called Bar as a part of the package Foo,
     the name of the directory is Foo_Bar. So the resulting path
     is <filename>pear/Foo_Bar</filename>.
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="I have written a PHP module in C. What are the rules 
   of including those in PEAR?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Stig Bakken"/>
    <para>
     If you just want to make a simple extension, put it in
     pear/PECL/extname (that is where extensions from php4/ext/extname
     will be moved). If you want to write an extension following PEAR's
     function/class naming, put it in pear/FOO_Bar or whatever the right
     name is.
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry> 
 
  <qandaentry>
   <question title="What's PECL?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Martin Jansen"/>
    <para>
     This used to be the former name of PEAR: PHP Extension and Code Library 
     (pronounced "pickle").
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry> 
   
  <qandaentry>
   <question title="Why is PEAR seperated into pear/ and php4/pear/?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Martin Jansen"/>
    <para>
     The first elements of PEAR were stored in the directory php4/pear
     and so they were bundled with each new PHP release.<break/>
     For future releases of PEAR this isn't workable because PEAR will
     become to big to be bundled with every release of PHP. So there was
     a decision to commit all new elements to an own top level directory
     pear. The other elements which are currently remaining in php4/pear
     will be moved to the new top level directory soon. Only the PEAR
     base classes which are needed by most PEAR elements and the installer
     system will remain in php4/pear and will be bundled with every new
     release automatically.
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="Why does the directory structure of pear/ and php4/pear/ differ?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Stig Bakken"/>
    <para>
     The directory structure of <filename>php4/pear/</filename>
     matches that of the install tree (by default
     <filename>/usr/local/lib/php</filename>), and are organized as a
     simple hierarchy.  However, the directory structure of
     <filename>pear/</filename> is based on what package the files
     belong to.  Where files are located in each package directory is
     completely independent from where they end up being installed,
     this is all determined by the package description file.
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="Why a flat directory structure instead of a deep?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Stig Bakken"/>
    <para>
     A deep directory structure does not go well with the idea of
     having separately managed packages with their own release
     cycles, CVS access control and so on.
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="Can I commit experimental/unstable stuff?" />
    <answer>
     <author name="Alexander Merz"/>
     <para>
      Yes. But make sure, that you mark up the experimental/unstable
      status of the project in the documention. The best place to do
      this is in the package.xml in the &lt;status&gt;-tag.
      The values for this tag are
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>alpha</term>
	<listitem>
	 <simpara>
         early stages of development, all things could change (API,
         behavoir) without notice, expect lots of bugs
        </simpara>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>beta</term>
	<listitem>
	 <simpara>
         API should normally not change, usable software, expect bugs
        </simpara>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>devel</term>
	<listitem>
	 <simpara>
         a release for other developers who want early access to test
	  and give feedback, code quality may vary from pre-alpha to
	  stable
        </simpara>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>stable</term>
	<listitem>
	 <simpara>
         the software was tested, the API fixed, the documention
         wrote and is the recommended release for users and
         production enviroments
        </simpara>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>snapshot</term>
	<listitem>
	 <simpara>
         a CVS snapshot from a certain date
        </simpara>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
      <simplelist>
     </simplelist>
     ( list by Tomas V.V. Cox )
    </para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry> 
   <question title="Am I expected to add examples and/or test files to my package and
   where to store them?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Alexander Merz"/>
    <para>
     Examples are a good idea, especially when your class has a complex API. But examples
     are only a part of a documention. Don't create examples instead of a documentation.
     You should store the documention and the examples in a sub directory 'docs' of the package 
     directory.
    </para>
    <para>
     Test scripts are recommanded when your class has to by compiled, requires
     special extentions/ programs or needs correct installed additional files
     (i.e. templates, graphics). Store them in sub directory called 'tests'.
    </para>
   </answer>  
  </qandaentry>
   
  <qandaentry>
   <question title="Are different packages or classes with similar features 
   allowed?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Alexander Merz"/>
    <para>
        There is no problem with competitive packages, but we want to avoid
        pollution with 10 template classes, 7 different mail classes, and 3
        different layers for databases doing the same only with different 
        function names. 
    </para>
    <para>
        First of all, do a reality check: Why do I want to commit a new package?
        Really bad answers are <quote>To see my name in PEAR</quote> or  
        <quote>I didn't understand the API of the existing class</quote>.
    </para>
    <para>        
        A good reason for a new class is often, that you are missing a function, 
        behaviour or speed in an existing implementation. In this case, you 
        should take a look at this class, if it possible to extend this class. 
        If not, then you have a good reason to commit a new class. <quote>If
        not</quote> means, it isn't possible to add the required functionality 
        without changing the basics of this class.
    </para>
    <para>
        If you write a new class, try to keep API compatibility with existing 
        classes as far as possible! If it isn't  possible to keep the class 
        compatible himself, try to create a wrapper class to keep compatibility. 
        Don't care, if this wrapper needs a lot of time or memory, a wrapper 
        class only has to keep compatibility and make migration easier.
    </para>
    <para>
        Committing a competitive class has to be announced on the <ulink
        url="http://pear.php.net/support.php">PEAR developers mailinglist</ulink>!
    </para>         
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="How should I write the documentation?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Tomas V.V.Cox"/>
    <para>
     The selected standard to write the API documentation is <ulink url="http://phpdoc.de/">
     PHPDoc</ulink>. For the rest of the documentation like the manual or usage examples, the
     recommended formats are plain text, HTML or <ulink url="http://docbook.org/">DocBook</ulink>.
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="What is the difference between a package, a class and a file?" />
   <answer>
    <author name=""/> <!-- will be Stig Sæther Bakken one time //-->
    <para>
     There is no answer yet.
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="I have a question about PEAR. Where should I ask?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Martin Jansen"/>
    <simplelist>
     <member>General questions about the usage of PEAR components should be posted
     to the mailing list <ulink url="mailto:pear-general@lists.php.net">pear-general@lists.php.net</ulink>.
     </member>

     <member>
     All technical discussions concerning the development of PEAR
     components should be posted to <ulink url="mailto:pear-dev@lists.php.net">
     pear-dev@lists.php.net</ulink>.
     </member>

     <member>
      Question concerning the website can be sent to
      <ulink url="mailto:pear-webmaster@php.net">pear-webmaster@php.net</ulink>.
     </member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>
    Information on subscribing this mailing lists can be found <ulink url="/support.php">here</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
    On all mailing lists mentioned above the language is english and the way
    you ask questions should always be polite :-).
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="A required package includes a package, my package needs it too. 
                    Should I include it again?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Alexander Merz"/>
    <para>
     Yes. You should include every package, you need with <function>require_once</function> 
     or <function>include_once</function>, also when it is included already by another package
    </para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry> 

  <qandaentry>
   <question title="Does PEAR work on windows?" />
   <answer>
    <author name="Martin Jansen"/>
    
    <para>To make PEAR work on Windows, you simple need to add the
    PEAR installation dir (e.g. c:\php\pear) to the include_path
    directive in your php.ini.</para>
    
    <para>Note: There are some classes (like Schedule/At.php), that do
    not work on Windows, because they use *nix specific commands.</para>
   </answer>
  </qandaentry>
 </qandaset>

</article>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-namecase-general:t
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
-->
